<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-04-07T12:01:59+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Cora Barrett</title><subtitle>This is a website by Cora Barrett discussing her musings on UK property planning.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Are we planning for affordable homes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/planning/housing-white-paper/housing/affordable%20housing/2017/04/06/are-we-planning-for-affordable-homes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are we planning for affordable homes" /><published>2017-04-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/planning/housing-white-paper/housing/affordable%20housing/2017/04/06/are-we-planning-for-affordable-homes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/planning/housing-white-paper/housing/affordable%20housing/2017/04/06/are-we-planning-for-affordable-homes.html">&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION: Commentary on affordable housing policy set out in the Housing White Paper.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/fixing-our-broken-housing-market&quot;&gt;Housing White Paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-we-planning-for-affordable-homes&quot;&gt;Are we planning for affordable homes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often been asked: “What do you mean by affordable housing?”  There are a number of affordable housing tenures aimed at giving those who are unable to rent or buy homes at market prices. However increasingly, and in particular in London, the “affordable tenures”, are still unaffordable to many. The White Paper places great emphasis on increasing the number of affordable homes, but I doubt the measures set out will actually provide the truly affordable homes desperately needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Joseph Roundtree Foundation recently published an interesting report on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jrf.org.uk/report/tackling-poverty-through-housing-and-planning-policy-city-regions&quot;&gt;Tackling Poverty Through Housing and Planning Policy&lt;/a&gt;. This report includes an interesting graphic on the impact of housing costs on poverty. Currently housing costs are pushing millions of people across the country, with the most acute rise in London. Unless we address the issue of providing truly affordable housing now this figure is likely to continue to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Housing White Paper’s main response to the challenge of providing affordable housing appears to be to increase the number of types of affordable housing to provide more affordable rent and ownership options. I assume the logic behind this is that increasing the number of types of affordable housing will improve the viability of providing a proportion of affordable homes on site. While I agree that there is likely to be a greater take up of the range of affordable products suggested, I do not believe this will result in the increase in the truly affordable housing needed to tackle the looming housing poverty crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the key issues associated with the affordable tenures is the link back to local market value. This is a particular concern with regard to the new tenure of “affordable private rented housing” which is to be provided as part of Build to Rent schemes and does not need to be owned by local authorities or registered providers. Build to Rent Schemes are often rented at a premium above local market values and may distort the calculation of local market value. In order to ensure there is no artificial inflation of local market value the figure should be set by local authorities and subject to an annual review. However a much better way to ensure housing provided is truly affordable would be to link costs back to local average household incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The affordable homeownership options do not address the increasing gap between those benefitting from large deposits provided by family or inheritance and those who do not. There have been many shared ownership properties for sale in London with full market value of over £1 million, meaning that a person who falls within the income cap would need to put down a substantial deposit to ensure monthly payments are affordable. Imposing an income threshold is meaningless without a cap on the maximum reasonable deposit a person on a certain income could have in order to make a property affordable. I have seen schemes in London with an income threshold of £30,000 but requiring a £90,000 deposit. It would take decades for a person on that income to save for that scale of deposit, and so to classify this type of housing as affordable is laughable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally the Housing White Paper does not seek to address the elephant in the room - viability. To those in the industry viability assessments are known as the dark arts, able to persuade local authorities that high value residential schemes are unable to provide target levels of affordable housing or make meaningful financial contributions for local authorities to provide affordable housing off-site. The potential to negotiate affordable housing as part of a planning application is increasing land values, as developers bidding on a site take a risk on this item. In order to avoid this the affordable housing requirement for all schemes should be set as a non-negotiable cost for development. House builders should be seeking cost efficiencies through modernising the construction industry and not by cutting out affordable housing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accept that it is not always possible to provide affordable on site, for example where a single block of flats is provided and it is not possible to provide two cores (sharing cores only leads to increased services charges for tenants of affordable housing). In such circumstances an affordable housing payment in lieu should still be acceptable to the local authority, however this payment should realistically cover the cost of building the required number of affordable housing units based on a robust business plan prepared by the local authority, which should include covering the cost of purchasing the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thresholds of affordable housing should be set based on local needs. However there may be some sites of particular strategic importance which require incentives to come forward. Such sites may include large brownfield town centre sites with contamination or other issues that have prevented development in the past. For such sites a local authority should consider setting a lower affordable housing threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary then, the Government should go further to ensure that we deliver truly affordable housing for the future. We should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linking affordable rents to average local incomes;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Placing a cap on the deposits required for affordable home ownership products linked to income thresholds; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removing viability considerations from affordable housing provision as part of new residential developments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Cora Barrett</name></author><summary type="html">DESCRIPTION: Commentary on affordable housing policy set out in the Housing White Paper.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The potential of planning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/planning/housing-white-paper/housing/2017/04/02/the-potential-of-planning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The potential of planning" /><published>2017-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-04-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/planning/housing-white-paper/housing/2017/04/02/the-potential-of-planning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/planning/housing-white-paper/housing/2017/04/02/the-potential-of-planning.html">&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION: Introduction to my blog.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-potential-of-planning&quot;&gt;The potential of planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been inspired to write this post following a recent review of the Housing White Paper. While it is positive to see the Government is attempting to tackle the spiralling problems in the housing market, reading through the document I found myself questioning whether or not any of the policies would actually lead to the step change in housing delivery required. Many of the proposals amount to little more than tinkering with a broken system when in reality we should be taking this opportunity to consider how we can make a system that is fit for purpose for now and the future. Over this series of blogs I will consider responses to the consultation queries raised in the White Paper document and will set out the questions I believe we should be asking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Cora Barrett</name></author><summary type="html">DESCRIPTION: Introduction to my blog.</summary></entry></feed>